Developers before Docker and containers were like cavemen.
도커와 컨테이너 이전 시대에 살던 개발자들은 그냥 원시인과 다를 바가 없었습니다
When starting a new job, they'd spend the whole day setting up their development environment.
어디 새로 취업하면 개발 환경 세팅을 맞추느라 하루 종일 삽질했었구요
Updating the development environment always broke something, so we prayed it wouldn't.
개발 환경 업데이트를 하면 항상 뭐가 망가지기 때문에 그러지 말라고 열심히 기도하기도 했구요
And when I tried to run my code on the server,
그리고 내가 코드 짠 걸 서버 컴퓨터에 보내서 실행만 하려고 하면
the computer would crash or explode, so we even performed rituals before deploying.
컴퓨터가 에러나고 폭발하고 그런 일들이 많아서 배포하기 전에 고사도 지내고 그랬습니다
But after Docker and containers came along, that's mostly gone.
하지만 도커와 컨테이너가 등장하고 나서 이 짓거리가 거의 없어졌구요
That's probably why Docker has been the most used tool for developers for years.
그래서 그런지 개발자들이 가장 많이 쓰는 툴 1위를 매년 도커가 차지하고 있구요
And these days, whether you're looking at a coding book or downloading a deep learning model online,
그리고 또 요즘은 코딩 책을 보려고 해도 아니면 인터넷에서 딥러닝 모델을 다운받아서 돌리려고 해도
you often see Docker commands first.
도커 명령어부터 보이는 경우들이 많습니다
So, what is Docker? It's an OS-level virtualization technology based on Linux containers.
자 도커가 뭐냐면 리눅스 컨테이너를 기반으로 만든 OS 레벨의 가상화 기술인데
If I explain it like that, you'll all click the back button, so let's try to understand it easily.
이따구로 설명하면 다 뒤로가기 누르니까 쉽게 이해해보도록 합시다
Let's say you messed up while coding and opened a fried chicken restaurant in Seoul.
여러분들이 코딩하다가 망해가지고 서울에다가 이제 뭐 치킨집을 하나 차렸다고 칩시다
And it does well, so you want to open a branch in Busan.
근데 잘 돼가지고 이번에 부산에다가 분점을 내고 싶습니다
How would you operate the Busan branch?
그러면 부산 지점은 어떻게 운영할 거에요?
The easiest way is to just send your recipe and tell them to follow it exactly.
가장 쉽게 할 수 있는 게 내가 쓰던 레시피만 보내서 이걸 그대로 따라하라고 하는 거에요
You could do that, but it would be a disaster.
그래도 되겠지만 그러면 인생도 망하는 거구요
The kitchen facilities, tools, and ingredients in Busan are all different from Seoul, which means
자 부산이랑 서울이랑 주방 시설도 다르고 도구도 다르고 재료가 다르고 뭐 그러면
there will be a lot of problems in the cooking process.
조리 과정에서 문제도 많이 생길 거구요
And the taste will be slightly different.
맛도 살짝 달라질 수밖에 없습니다
So, to run a business properly, you'd prepare
그래서 제대로 장사를 하려면 여러분들이 이제 서울에서 쓰던
all the ingredients and recipes you used in Seoul like a meal kit and send them to Busan.
재료랑 레시피랑 뭐 이런 걸 전부 밀키트처럼 준비를 해서 그걸 부산으로 보내요
Then in Busan, they can just heat it up and serve it.
그 다음에 부산에서는 이걸 그냥 데우는 식으로만 운영하시면 되는 거에요
Most big franchise chicken restaurants operate like this, and it's the same when developing software.
좀 큰 프랜차이즈 치킨집들은 전부 이런 식으로 하는데 개발할 때도 똑같습니다
I often need to run the same code on different computers.
자 내가 같은 코드를요. 각각 다른 컴퓨터에서 실행해야 되는 경우들이 많은데
But if the code runs fine on my computer, and I just send it to another computer and try to run it,
근데 내 컴퓨터에서 코드가 잘 돌아간다고 자 이걸 다른 컴퓨터에 대충 보내서 실행을 하면
it often results in a disaster.
디제스터가 많이 일어납니다
Each computer has a different OS and different versions of the default programs installed.
컴퓨터마다 OS도 다르고 설치된 기본 프로그램들 버전도 다르고 그러니까요
If you don't want that, prepare the same OS and programs that you use,
그게 싫으면 여러분들이 쓰던 OS랑 프로그램이랑 이런 것들을 전부 똑같이 준비한 다음에
and then put your code on it and run it there.
그 다음에 코드를 그 위에 넣으세요. 그 위에서 실행하면 되는 거에요
To do this, we used to use VMs.
이러기 위해서 옛날엔 vm이란 걸 썼습니다
It's about installing another OS on top of an existing OS, but it's very heavy and doesn't perform well.
어떤 OS 위에다가 다른 OS를 설치하는 건데 굉장히 무겁고 성능도 좋지 않기 때문에
So, these days we use Docker and containers instead.
요즘은 그거 대신에 도커랑 컨테이너를 씁니다
With Docker, you can create a code meal kit.
자 도커를 쓰면 코드 밀키트 같은 걸 만들 수 있습니다
You can put everything in it: the OS, SDK, required programs, libraries, and code.
거기다가 OS 뭐 sdk 필요한 프로그램 라이브러리 코드 뭐 이런 걸 전부 담을 수 있구요
And with Docker, you can easily run the meal kit with just a click.
그리고 도커를 쓰면 그 밀키트를요. 버튼 딸깍 눌러서 쉽게 실행하는 것도 가능하구요
So, Docker is basically just a simple program that creates and runs code meal kits.
그래서 도커는 쉽게 말하면 그냥 코드 밀키트를요. 만들고 실행해주는 간단한 프로그램일 뿐이에요
And by the way, there is a virtual computer that runs the meal kit,
그리고 참고로 밀키트를 실행하고 있는 가상 컴퓨터가 있는데
and cool developers call this a container.
자 이런 걸 멋있는 개발자 말로 컨테이너라고 부르구요
But it's hard to understand just by talking, so let's take a quick look at how to use it.
근데 말로만 씨부리면 이해가 어렵기 때문에 대충 어떻게 쓰는지 살짝만 맛을 좀 보도록 합시다
To create a meal kit, you need a file.
자 밀키트를 어떻게 만드냐면 파일이 하나 필요합니다
It's called a Dockerfile.
도커 파일이라는 게 필요하구요
You write down what OS to use, what programs, libraries, and SDKs to install,
여기다가 어떤 OS를 쓸 건지 어떤 프로그램이랑 라이브러리랑 sdk를 설치할 건지
and how to run the code in it.
그리고 어떤 코드를 어떻게 실행할 건지 쭉 적을 수 있습니다
Then, with just one command, it's packaged up.
그 다음에 명령어 하나만 입력하면 포장이 되구요
And then you can run this meal kit with a single click.
그 다음에 클릭 한 번으로 이 밀키트를 실행할 수 있습니다
Then the code inside will run.
그러면 안에 있던 코드가 실행이 될 거예요
And it will run your code stably on the OS and working environment that you set in the Dockerfile.
근데 여러분이 도커 파일에서 설정했던 자 그 OS랑 작업 환경 라이브러리 그 위에서
The OS and the working environment, the library,
내 코드를 안정적으로 실행해 줄 거구요
That's it. That's how you use Docker and containers.
이게 도커와 컨테이너 사용법 끝이에요
You've learned it all.
다 배우신 거구요
After Docker and containers were discovered, developers started doing all sorts of amazing things with them.
도커와 컨테이너가 발견되고 나서 자 개발자들도 이걸 써서 온갖 신기한 짓을 하기 시작을 했습니다
Because meal kits made deployment much easier, the way servers are developed these days is that
자 밀키트 덕분에 이제 배포 같은 것도 되게 쉬워졌기 때문에 자 요즘은 어떤 식으로 서버를 개발하냐면
in the past, server functions were all crammed into one program,
어 예전엔 서버 기능을 하나의 프로그램 안에 다 쑤셔 넣었었는데
but now it's split into multiple programs.
자 지금은 자에게 쪼개서 여러 프로그램으로 이렇게 나누기 시작을 했습니다
This is called MSA and it's the bread and butter of the backend these days.
이걸 MSA 라고 하는데 요즘 백엔드의 밥줄이 되었구요
And because building, testing, and deploying programs
그리고 프로그램을 빌드하고 테스트하고 배포하는 작업이
has become easy enough for even elementary school kids to do, thanks to Docker,
도커 덕분에 초딩도 할 수 있을 정도가 됐기 때문에
more and more places are starting to adopt automatic deployment.
이제 자동 배포 같은 걸 도입하기 시작하는 곳들이 매우 많아졌구요
And with Docker, you can easily install
그리고 도커를 쓰면 원하는 프로그램을요
the program you want on the version and OS you want, and even cleanly remove it.
원하는 버전 그리고 원하는 OS 위에 되게 쉽게 설치하고 깔끔하게 삭제까지도 할 수 있기 때문에
This has led to the emergence of developers with germophobia who don't want to install anything on their local computers.
내 로컬 컴퓨터에 뭐 설치하기 싫어하는 결벽증 걸린 개발자들이 생기기 시작했구요
If you're curious about what Docker really is, it's nothing special.
도커의 실체가 궁금하시면 실은 별거 아니구요
There was originally a lightweight virtualization technology in Linux itself.
리눅스 자체에 원래 가벼운 가상화 기술 같은 게 있었는데
Using that, you can create something called a container.
이런 걸 쓰면 컨테이너라는 걸 만들 수 있구요
Just think of it as a virtual computer.
그냥 가상 컴퓨터라고 생각하면 될 것 같습니다
There are programs that help ordinary people create them easily.
이걸 일반 사람들도 편하게 만들 수 있게 도와주는 프로그램 같은 것도 있구요
Docker is just a tool that makes it easy for even a dog to use these things.
근데 이것들을 심지어 개도 편하게 쓸 수 있게 만들어 놓은 게 도커라는 툴일 뿐이에요
And by the way, there are some alternatives to Docker.
그래서 참고로 도커 대신 쓸 수 있는 대용품도 몇 가지 있구요
Or you can even run Linux containers directly without Docker.
아니면 도커 없이 직접 리눅스 컨테이너를 띄우는 것도 가능합니다
Of course, there are downsides.
당연히 단점도 있습니다
You have to take care of new security issues.
자, 새로운 보안 이슈들도 챙겨야 되구요
If you have a lot of containers, you need people to manage them.
컨테이너가 많아지면 그걸 관리하는 인력도 필요하고
And server costs can be higher than you think at the beginning.
서버 비용 같은 것도 초창기엔 생각보다 많이 들 거구요
Also, when you need to store data permanently and stably, containers might not be a good idea.
그리고 뭔가 데이터를 영구적으로 안정적으로 저장해야 될 땐 컨테이너가 별로일 수도 있습니다
But the most important thing is that the learning curve for coding beginners has become steeper.
근데 가장 중요한 건 코딩 초보자들의 러닝커브가 심해졌다는 거구요
Because Docker is so popular, some lectures and books make you set up Docker from the start of your coding journey.
하도 도커가 좋다니까 코딩 입문할 때 도커 세팅부터 시키는 강의나 책들도 있는데
To give you an analogy of this,
근데 그런 짓거리를 좀 비유를 해보자면
it's like learning to cook by going to a pre-made kitchen set,
내가 요리를 배운다고 하면서 남이 다 만들어 놓은 세트장에 가서
taking out a chicken meal kit, opening it, and frying it.
치킨 밀키트를 가져와서 이렇게 뜯어서 튀겨보기 이 정도만 하는 거잖아요
If you want to do only that until you die, then go ahead.
여러분들이 그것만 하다가 죽고 싶으면 그러시면 되는데
But if you want to create your own chicken recipe, make your own meal kit, and open your own branch,
근데 나중에 나만의 치킨 요리를 만들어서 나만의 밀키트도 만들고 나만의 분점도 내고 그러고 싶으면
it's also important to try cooking on your own without relying on someone else's meal kit.
남의 밀키트 같은 거 도움 없이 직접 내가 요리를 해보는 것도 중요하구요
So, when you're starting to code, you should fight with your own computer directly without Docker, like a UFC match.
그러니까 코딩 입문을 하실 땐 도커 도움 없이 내 컴퓨터랑 직접 싸우면서 UFC를 한번 해보란 소리에요
That experience is necessary for you to confidently write Dockerfiles, build, and deploy later on.
그런 경험이 있어야 나중에 이제 도커 파일을 자신있게 작성해서 이렇게 빌드하고 배포하고 그럴 수 있는 거예요
But this isn't a time to learn coding,
근데 지금은 코딩 배우는 시간이 아니기 때문에
so I'll stop with the nagging since we are here to learn Docker, a simple tool.
자 도커라는 간단한 툴을 배우는 시간이기 때문에 잔소리는 여기까지 하고요
Now, I've mainly prepared how to use Docker well on your own,
이제 도커를요 혼자 알아서 이렇게 잘 쓸 수 있는 방법을 주로 준비해 봤으니까
so you can learn these things.
이런 것들 배워 가시면 될 것 같습니다
And later, let's also learn how to use Docker Compose and orchestration tools.
그 다음에 뒤에 가서 도커 컴포즈랑 오케스트레이션 툴 사용법까지 좀 알아보도록 합시다